<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's safety, or, A bridle to the French King proposing a sure method for encouraging navigation, and raising qualified seamen for the well manning Their Majesties fleet on any occasion, in a months time, without impressing, and a competent provision for all such as shall be wounded in service against the enemy, either in Their in Their Majesties ships of war, privatiers, or merchant men, to encourage the better defending them : also an in-flight into the advantages may be made by the herring and other fisheries, in respect to the breeding of seamen, and otherwise : together with a proposal for the maintenance and education of the male children ... : also encouragement for commanders of men of war, privatiers and seamen, in taking any ship, or effects of the enemies, and all to be done, without any sensible charge or burthern to the kingdom / by Captain George St. Lo...</title>
            <author>St. Lo, George, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21733</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12226824</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12226824</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 925:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's safety, or, A bridle to the French King proposing a sure method for encouraging navigation, and raising qualified seamen for the well manning Their Majesties fleet on any occasion, in a months time, without impressing, and a competent provision for all such as shall be wounded in service against the enemy, either in Their in Their Majesties ships of war, privatiers, or merchant men, to encourage the better defending them : also an in-flight into the advantages may be made by the herring and other fisheries, in respect to the breeding of seamen, and otherwise : together with a proposal for the maintenance and education of the male children ... : also encouragement for commanders of men of war, privatiers and seamen, in taking any ship, or effects of the enemies, and all to be done, without any sensible charge or burthern to the kingdom / by Captain George St. Lo...</title>
                  <author>St. Lo, George, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Miller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes advertisement.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy.</term>
               <term>France. --  Marine.</term>
               <term>Navigation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Navigation --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>England</hi>'s Safety: Or, a Bridle to the <hi>French</hi> King, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of ships, the union flag, navigational instruments and ship's tools</figDesc>
                  <p>IN THESE LYE THE STRENGTH AND GLORY OF ENGLAND</p>
                  <p>This Encouraged, <hi>England</hi> muſt Flouriſh</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Miller,</hi> at the Gilded Acorn in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard, MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ENGLAND</hi>'s SAFETY: OR, A BRIDLE TO THE French King.</p>
            <p>PROPOSING A Sure Method for Encouraging NAVIGATION, and Raiſing Qualified Seamen for the well Manning Their Majeſties FLEET on any Occaſion, in a Months Time, without Impreſſing; And a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Proviſion for all ſuch as ſhall be Wounded in Service againſt the Enemy, either in their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Ships of War, Privatiers, or Merchant-Men, to Encourage the better Defending them.</p>
            <p>ALSO An In-ſight into the Advantages may be made by the Herring and other Fiſheries, in reſpect to the Breeding of Seamen, and otherwiſe. Together with a PROPOSAL for the Maintenance and Education of the Male Children of all ſuch as ſhall be Kill'd in Service, both Seamen and Officers; And a Proviſion for Gentlemens Younger Sons, and the Sons of Commanders Kill'd in the Service, to qualifie them for the Sea, in order to make Officers.</p>
            <p>ALSO Encouragement for Commanders of Men of War, Privatiers and Seamen, in Taking any Ship, or Effects of the Enemies, and all to be done, without any ſenſible Charge or Burthen to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>By Captain <hi>George S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Lo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Miller,</hi> at the <hi>Gilded Acorn</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, where Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and others may be furniſhed with Bound Books of moſt Sorts, Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Speeches, and other ſorts of Diſcourſes, and State-Matters; as alſo Books of Divinity, Church-Government, Human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Sermons on moſt Occaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:3"/>
            <head>To the <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EENS</hi> moſt Excellent <hi>MAJESTIES.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAVING (as I humbly conceive) found out a ſure Method for the well Manning Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Fleet, (the Strength and Glory of Your Dominions, and Terror of Your Enemies) on any Occaſion in a Months Time, without the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or Charge of Impreſſing; As alſo a Method for the Breeding of Seamen, and Encouraging Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without Charge to Your <hi>Majeſties;</hi> I humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to lay the ſame at Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royal Feet, in hopes of Your Gracious Acceptation and Countenance of my Endeavours, for the Service of Your <hi>Majeſties,</hi> the Eaſe of Your Subjects, and the General Benefit of Trade. That <hi>GOD</hi> may ever Bleſs, Preſerve and Proſper Your Sacred <hi>Majeſties,</hi> for the Good of theſe Your Kingdoms, as well as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Benefit of Chriſtendom; Shall always be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties Moſt Obedient, Dutiful and Devoted Subject and Servant, <hi>George St. LO.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the <hi>Lords</hi> Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal, and <hi>Commons</hi> in Parliament Aſſembled.</head>
            <p>I Cannot but give this Honourable Aſſembly ſome ſhort Account of the Tyrannous Inſults and Barbarous Threats of Our Enemies, (the <hi>French)</hi> in Particular againſt theſe Two Houſes of Parliament, at the beginning of the War.</p>
            <p>IT being my Misfortune to be Diſabled and Taken at Sea, in the Year 1689. I was carried to <hi>Breſt</hi> under very hard uſage, and nothing could I hear, but of having my Self and Men ſent to the <hi>Gallies,</hi> and that they did not queſtion but in a Twelve Months time, to have all the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> there, to Row their King in a Galley, uſing the moſt Reproachful Names to this Auguſt Aſſembly, that their Malice and Madneſs could think of; and ſo far they proceeded in their Barbarity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of Victory, that they took upwards of Seven Hundred <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Priſoners, (part of them my Ship's Company) Hand-cuff'd them two and two together, fastning Sixty Couple in a Rope, in that manner, driving them from <hi>Breſt</hi> and other Places, to <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> being ſeveral Hundred Miles, Beating, Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and ſo hardly uſing them, that ſeveral of them died under their hands: And when they came to <hi>Thoulon,</hi> hearing of the Succeſs of Their Majesties Arms in <hi>Ireland,</hi> they changed their Reſolution of putting them into the Galleys, but travelled them back again to <hi>Rochfort,</hi> under ſuch miſerable, harſh and ſevere uſage, with Hunger, Cold, Travelling, and Beating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That
<pb facs="tcp:56570:4"/> many of them Died by the way, who were then knock'd out of the Irons, and left often in the Fields without Burial; And when any of them broke Priſon, (which their Miſery forc'd them to, deſiring rather to dye than live ſo) their Guard when they took them, would Chain them to a Wall without ſhelter from the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and there let them lie Languiſhing for ſeveral days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as particularly <hi>John Hutchin's,</hi> Yeoman of my Powder-Room, and many others: And for my own part, they took Me out of the Hoſpital at <hi>Breſt,</hi> before half Cur'd of my Wounds, and would have carry'd me on Horſe-back, though the Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons declar'd it would certainly Kill me; at length the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions prevail'd to have me carried in a Litter, with Lieutenant <hi>Walker,</hi> one of my Lieutenants, who was likewiſe Wounded; They Carry'd us thus Eight Days in Company with three Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whoſe Noſes were ſlit an Inch up, their Cheeks burnt with a <hi>Flower-de-luce,</hi> their Hair cut off, and their Ears cut, with their Legs tied under the Horſes Belly, and their Hands chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet they were better mounted than thoſe in Company with me, to whom they would neither allow Stick nor Spur; Their Names were Lieutenant <hi>William Clutterbuck,</hi> (one of my Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants) Mr. <hi>Rowley</hi> the Vice Admiral of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Carbonnell,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant of <hi>French</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who was first taken up under pretence of being a Spy, and ſtill detained in Priſon, and now pretend Debt upon him. We were guarded with the Povost Marine, and four Arches, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out by the way, That I was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lord they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſo that all the Country People came flocking to ſee me. When we came to <hi>Nantz,</hi> they clapt us up in the Caſtle, where there were two Hugonots and a Priest, one Monſieur <hi>La Noa,</hi> that had been a Priſoner Two and Twenty Years, Seven Years in a Dungeon (where he never had any Light but while he Eat) Sixteen Years before brought to Tryal, and then becauſe too old to go to the <hi>Gallies,</hi> they Condemn'd him to perpetual Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and all for writing a Book Reflecting on the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Paris;</hi> and though they could not prove it upon him, yet they uſed him ſo ſeverely, it being the Barbarous Principle of the Cruel <hi>French King,</hi> rather to puniſh twenty Innocent
<pb facs="tcp:56570:5"/> Perſons, than let one, they think Guilty, Eſcape: They would not allow us any Proviſion though we ſent to the Governor, unleſs we would give half a Crown a Day each; then we deſired the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance only of Bread and Water, telling them we had no Mony, but for all that they would not allow us any without paying for it, and Six-pence a Day found us Four Bread, which we were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to give or ſtarve; thus we liv'd on Bread and Water Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Days, and then the other Three conſented to pay for other Victuals; but becauſe I found ſuch living did me good for my Wounds, I continued it Five and Twenty Days, with the help of two Pound of <hi>Cheeſe</hi> which I had, unknown to my Guard; but if we had had no Mony we must have ſtarved for Want. When I came to eat Meat, my Wounds growing worſe, I was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to take Phyſick, and being adviſed by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to take care I were not Poiſoned therewith, when my Phyſick was brought, I called the rest of my Company, and deſired them to bear Witneſs, That if I were Poiſoned, it were in Drinking King <hi>William</hi>'s Health, and thereupon I drank the ſame, which being told the Governor by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Rowley,</hi> and notice ſent to <hi>Paris,</hi> An Order came to take me from the rest of my Company, and put me into a Dungeon; but the Governor being a Man of more Conſcience than the rest, becauſe there was no Dungeon but what was ſo wet would ſoon have kill'd me, He put me in a Tower (the Walls twenty Foot thick) Archt above and below, and the Windows made up, ſave only a little Light twelve Foot high, where I lay a lone very diſconſolately, three or four Months, when Mr. <hi>Skelton</hi> coming thither, got me liberty to walk in the Castle, which being known at <hi>Paris,</hi> an Order came to ſend me to <hi>Angiers,</hi> and then I had Ten-pence a Day paid me for all the time I was at <hi>Nantz,</hi> which was the only Mony I received of the <hi>French</hi> all the while I was in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Angiers</hi> I lay Cloſe Priſoner in the Caſtle fifteen Months more, under a moſt Cruel and Tyrannical Governor, Monſieur <hi>Doteſhon</hi> (formerly one of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi>'s Guard) who would receive the Sacrament every Week, and yet as ſoon as he
<pb facs="tcp:56570:5"/> came out of the Chappel, and ſometimes even within it, would beat or abuſe the Priſoners, or do ſome wicked thing or other, on any the leaſt occaſion.</p>
            <p>There were in Priſon fourteen Perſons,<note place="margin">
                  <list>
                     <item>The Dutcheſs de la <hi>Force,</hi> three Years in Priſon.</item>
                     <item>Mr. de <hi>Croſnier,</hi> five Years.</item>
                     <item>Mr. de la <hi>Brifardiere</hi> two Years.</item>
                     <item>Mr. de <hi>Malle,</hi> three Years for Religion.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Mademoiſelle <hi>Robert.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Mademoiſelle <hi>Voiſon</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Me. <hi>Katharine</hi> le Roy.</item>
                           <item>Me. <hi>Manon Soignart.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Me. du <hi>Pleſſis.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Me. <hi>Paulain.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Me. <hi>Bellefuille.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Me. <hi>Carnay,</hi> Aged 100 Years.</item>
                           <item>Me de <hi>la Porte,</hi> Aged 80 Years.</item>
                        </list> In Priſon 12 years on ſuſpicion of Poyſoning, but can have no Tryal or Hearing.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> ſome for Religion, and the reſt on other Pretences; among whom were People of very good Quality, whoſe Names are in the Margin; they have ſome of them been in Priſon ten or twelve Years, ſome more, ſome leſs, and ſome of them Eighty and an Hundred years of Age, who are never permitted to Write or receive any Letters from their Friends, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Dutcheſs <hi>de la Force,</hi> tho her Husband the Duke (by his great Age and Hardſhip in the <hi>Baſtile)</hi> was forced to turn his Religion, yet they will not ſuffer him to Write to his Dutcheſs, nor her to Write to him.</p>
            <p>This Governor by his own contrivance to Puniſh the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, had a Door made to the outſide of each Priſon Window, which upon every ſlight occaſion, he would cauſe to be Locked up, that the Priſoners had no manner of Light ſometimes for ſix or ſeven Months together.</p>
            <p>While I was at <hi>Angiers,</hi> there was a Proteſtant Marqueſs Condemned to the Gallies for breaking out of Priſon, he was Chained to a <hi>Turk,</hi> that had hardly Rags to cover him; in this Manner he was carried to the Galleys, and then made to Strip, and Row with the reſt of the Slaves.</p>
            <p>The Taxes upon the People are ſo Prodigious, that a poor Shoemaker at <hi>Angiers</hi> (one <hi>Mathurine Gainer)</hi> that had a Wife and three Children, and paid but Twenty Shillings a Year Rent, was rated a Noble; and tho he offered to part with all he
<pb facs="tcp:56570:6"/> had for five Shillings, yet they ſent Soldiers to Quarter upon him till he paid; (which is their uſual method of raiſing Taxes) who taking away what he had, the poor Man by Charity, got enough to pay the Tax; but yet for ſaying he would write to the King about it, he was clap'd into a Dungeon in the ſame Caſtle where I was, and there kept three Weeks, and then upon the Supplication of his Wife, he was permitted to work in the Paſſage to the Dungeon, to keep his Children from Starving: And according to the Ability of the Perſons, they ſend Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to Rifle and Tyrannize over them till they pay their Taxes, and when I came away, they were going to lay a Tax upon <hi>Saboes,</hi> or Wooden Shoes, beſides four Pence upon a Hat tho it coſt but half a Crown, and Taxes upon Chriſtnings and Funerals.</p>
            <p>☞ There was likewiſe Priſoner at <hi>Angiers,</hi> one <hi>Mr. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman, who being in the Academy before the War, was at the beginning of the War, taken up as a Spy, tho then but Fifteen Years of Age, and kept ſo cloſely, that they would neither let me ſee him when he was Sick, nor he ſee me when I was Sick, only when I was coming away, with much ado, I got to ſee him, where he lay in the Common-Goal in a ſad Condition, and now I hear, he is removed to the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> and no Exchange will be allowed for him, tho there was a Priſoner ſent hence by mutual Agreement, for him, two Years ſince, who was kept there and yet he not delivered; and thus we ſee what little regard the <hi>French</hi> have to their Word, in performing either Articles or Treaties.</p>
            <p>At my coming away, I went to viſit the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners at <hi>Dinan</hi> in <hi>Brittany,</hi> where they lay in a moſt miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; two lay Dead at the Door, and had ſo lain four and twenty Hours; the Place Stunk ſo I was not able to go in; and with their hard <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage, Seven hundred have been Buried out of that Priſon ſince this War; which computed with thoſe Dead at <hi>Rochfort</hi> and other Places, we cannot reckon to have loſt leſs than Two thouſand good Seamen, by the ill Treatment
<pb facs="tcp:56570:6"/> they have had in <hi>France:</hi> And notwithſtanding the General Exchange agreed on, they continue their wonted Barbarity to our Seamen as much as ever: And yet to the Honor of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sailers, I never found (notwithſtanding all their ill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage by Hunger, Beating and otherwiſe) that any of them went into that Kings Service, tho much Sollicited to it by the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> and Sir <hi>William Jennings;</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Fitz James,</hi> who is Stiled Grand Prior of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> went to Sea the two laſt years, yet there was not Fifty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seamen in their whole Fleet; which may ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute a popular Miſtake among us, that the French have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of our Seamen in their Service: Indeed, there are three Privateers belonging to King <hi>James,</hi> that were ſet out of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> when he was there, that are Manned with <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as they at firſt gave out I was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lord, ſo I found afterwards their Demands were accordingly for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe, for they firſt refuſed thirty Seamen in Exchange for me, then they refuſed two Captains <hi>(Pecarr</hi> and <hi>Buſheen)</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they demanded Captain <hi>St. Mariae</hi> and four <hi>Scotch</hi> Captains that lay Condemned in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and when that was conſented to, then they demanded Lieutenant General <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milton</hi> for me, and would not be content to take the Earl of <hi>Clancarty,</hi> or any of the other Priſoners in the Tower; and now after all, this Value put upon me by my Enemies, I ſhould be very glad to be thought Serviceable at Home, as I deſire to be, and hope I may in this.</p>
            <p>They took on Board me, one <hi>John Denny</hi> a <hi>French Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> who was Settled and Married in <hi>England;</hi> him they Condemned to be Hang'd at <hi>Raines,</hi> but afterwards gave him his Life to Serve them Ten Years. Now ſince there is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Exchange, and that we Releaſe all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> of their Party that we Take, I think it my Duty in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to plead for his being Demanded, and ſent for back, that he may return to his Family.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:7"/>
            <p> And here it may not be amiſs to let theſe Honourable Houſes know, what care the <hi>French</hi> King took to keep an account of what Expence he was at upon the account of <hi>Ireland;</hi> for that he had a Commiſſary on purpoſe to take and keep an Account of all the Charges he was at in all things relating thereto; and it may be eaſily imagined why he did ſo: One time it happened that the Governor of <hi>Angiers</hi> ſent for me, and in Diſcourſe told me what it had coſt the King his Maſter on the account of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which amounted to a great many Millions of <hi>Livres,</hi> which I put down for a Memorandum, but loſt the paper, and the Sum I have forgot; but the Governor told me, <hi>When King</hi> James <hi>got</hi> England <hi>again, he would pay the</hi> French <hi>King all the Expences he had been at on his Account, or give him</hi> Ireland <hi>for it.</hi> And another time a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman being permitted by the Governor to Diſcourſe me, and I not fearing to ſpeak, as knowing I could not well be uſed worſe than I was, told him, They were all Slaves to their King, but could not ſee it, like a Dog that never complains for want of a Hat, becauſe he never wore one. He ſaid, <hi>If they were Slaves, yet their Comfort was, they ſhould e'er long have us to be their Slaves.</hi> Another time the Governor ſent for me to tell me <hi>Plymouth</hi> was Surrendred to them, and that it was done by the Deputy-Governor, upon which I Smiled at the Conceit; he being extraordinarily deſirous to know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I would not believe it, I told him, That Governors here were not ſo Arbitrary as they in <hi>France;</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, a True <hi>Engliſhman</hi> had as much an Antipathy to a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> as a Maſtiff Dog had to a Bull; upon which he very angrily remanded me to Priſon.</p>
            <p>Salt is there Ninepence per Pound, which all People muſt take at that rate, and what quantity they are allotted; and muſt not diſpoſe of any to a Neighbour or Friend; and poor People that are not able to Buy, will watch an opportunity when any Salt Fiſh is laid a Freſhening, to get the Water to make Pottage, but the <hi>Goblees,</hi> which are Officers appointed to look
<pb facs="tcp:56570:7"/> after the Revenue of Salt, will throw it down the Kennel to prevent the Poor having that ſmall Advantge.</p>
            <p>If any Perſon be found Stealing the Cuſtom of Salt, though never ſo ſmall, they must pay an Hundred Crowns for the first Offence, or go to the <hi>Gallies;</hi> but if they do it a Second time, nothing can prevent their being ſent to the <hi>Gallies;</hi> and thus the <hi>French</hi> King breeds Slaves of his own, without buying <hi>Turks, Moors,</hi> or <hi>Negroes;</hi> for by the help of theſe, and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that break Priſon, he finds almoſt ſufficient for that uſe.</p>
            <p>The manner of his Dragooning his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects is this, When any one would not comply with the Priests in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, Dragoons were ſent to Quarter upon them, according to their Rank or Degree; which Dragoons would not be content with Free Quarters; but the Oppreſſed Hoſt was forced, for Quietneſs, to give them a Piſtole, or two Crowns a Day, in that manner waſting their Eſtates till all was gone; then the Poor Men would endeavour to make their Eſcape out of ſuch Miſery: But the Dragoons having a ſtrict Eye over them, would certainly keep them while any thing was left, and then carry them to Priſon.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King to decoy thoſe poor People, at firſt aſſured them by his Officers, that if they would comply, they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament in both kinds, which prevail'd with many to turn; but then according to his wonted Broken Word, denied them the Cup, and allowed them only the Wafer; and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance are now in Priſon that have ſo been for ſeveral Years past on that Account, who fail not conſtantly to Pray for the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Their Majeſties Arms.</p>
            <p>And if this be their uſage to their own People, What may thoſe of our Nation expect, if ever they ſhould be ſo wretchedly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy (which God prevent) to fall under their Power, which makes me admire that ſome People here ſhould ſo loſe their
<pb facs="tcp:56570:8"/> Senſes, as to Applaud or Entertain the least Thoughts of a <hi>French</hi> Government, which I could never imagine, till my Return to <hi>England;</hi> and therefore must impute it to the most Stupid ſort of Ignorance and Malice, and that they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to loſe after they have parted with their Brains, and that Love for their Country, Religion and Poſterity, which is natural to every true <hi>Engliſhman.</hi> I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt Faithful, and Obedient Servant, <hi>George St. LO.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:9"/>
            <head>Advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>☞ THE following <hi>Propoſals</hi> being humbly offer'd to the fartherance of Their Majeſties Service, as well in the ſpeedy and eaſy Manning the Fleet, as prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great Expence and Coſt of Impreſſing Seamen; It is not to be ſuppos'd, that Their Majeſties muſt loſe Their Royal Power and Prerogative of Impreſſing Seamen, and others, in Caſes of Exigencies, and when theſe Methods fail, which I have no reaſon as yet to doubt of. But it will be ſtill a further Encouragement for Seamen to come in Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiers for the ſake of Reward, when they ſhall ſtill be liable to a Preſs if they do not come in, and the fear of that will make them the more willing to go upon Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment rather than be forc'd to go without it; and that is alſo the Reaſon of the Merchants, Owners and Maſters of Ships, being willing this ſhould go forward, in that it will free them of the Charge of Protections, and prevent the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of their Voyages, by which they are now great loſers.</p>
            <p>☞ If the matter of theſe enſuing Sheets be not digeſted into that Method and Order I could wiſh, and that the Stile and Language be not Correct enough to appear in Print, I muſt beg the <hi>Reader</hi> to conſider, firſt, That it comes from a Sailer, whoſe Buſineſs it is rather to ſpeak Truth plain, than Neat and Elegant; Secondly, That the haſte I was in to get them Printed early enough for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to make them Uſeful for the enſuing Year, may be partly the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it; and Thirdly, That by my ill Uſage and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſuſtain'd in my Impriſonment in <hi>France,</hi> my <hi>Memory</hi> is prejudic'd; but ſure I am there is a good Foundation for wiſer Heads to work upon; and when the <hi>Parliament</hi> have it under their Conſideration, it will be at their Election to Enact this for a Year, or what time they pleaſe, and under what Regulations ſhall be thought fit, and according as it ſhall be found in that time it may either be made uſe of, or not.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposal">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56570:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ENGLAND</hi>'s GLORY, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> OR A PROPOSAL MADE BY <hi rend="blackletterType">Capt. George S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Lo.</hi> FOR THE Raiſing Twenty Thouſand SEAMEN, QUALIFIED, <hi>As here under-mentioned for the Service of Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties and the Kingdom, in Manning the Royal Navy on any Occaſion, (without Impreſſing) in a Month's time after ſetling the Office; Hereby hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propoſed for that purpoſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>THE Qualification of each Seaman, is, That he ſhall underſtand the Mechanick part of a Sailer, which is to Reef and Furl, and take his Trick at Helm, and be a Man at all Calls, properly called a <hi>Haulboling;</hi> ſo that half a Ships Complement of ſuch Men before the Maſt, will be ſufficient to well Man any Ship; for Maſters-Mates, Midſhip-Men, Quarter-Maſters, Quarter-Gunners, and other ſmall Officers, will go volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily with their reſpective Commanders; and ſeveral others (may be ſuppoſed) for Preferment, which will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56570:10"/> not be of this number. And therefore the ſaid Twenty Thouſand able Seamen (with the help of the Warrant-Officers, Voluntiers, Officers Servants, ſmall Officers, and Water-mens Apprentices, who are ſent by their Hall, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Sail-Makers, Armorers, Carpenters-Crew, and Chirurgions Crew,) will be ſufficient to Man Their Majeſties whole Fleet.</p>
               <p>This Method of bringing in Seamen without Impreſſing, will be of vaſt Advantage to the King and Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In ſaving the great Charge of Conduct-Mony, and Bounty-Mony.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In ſaving the Charge of hiring Smacks, Ketches, and other Veſſels, for Impreſſing of Seamen, which ſtand the King in 30 <hi>l.</hi> a Month each Veſſel one with another, or thereabouts; and of theſe each firſt and ſecond Rate Ship hath three or four, and a third and fourth Rate Ship hath one or two, beſides the Captains of each Ship according to the Rate and Bigneſs, have Impreſt Mony, ſome 100 <hi>l.</hi> ſome 50 <hi>l.</hi> ſome 20 <hi>l.</hi> Beſides bringing in their Bills of Charges and Disburſements, which have ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to two or three Hundred Pounds a Ship to my knowledge, all which, by the Method hereafter mentioned, may be ſaved to the Crown and Kingdom, which, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, Bounty and Impreſt-Mony, with the hiring of Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels as aforeſaid, cannot be reckoned to amount to leſs than 60000 <hi>l. per Annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this Method the King being aſſured of having Men rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Man his Fleet on any occaſion, in a Month's time, will ſave the vaſt Charges of keeping the great Ships in Pay all the Winter, and beſides prevent the Danger of ever being Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any Foreign Enemy; (as was like to have been this Year) for after the Summers Expedition is over, and the Fleet come in, it would be a great Encouragement to the Seamen to be paid off, and their Tickets paid at the ſame time, which would give them Credit at any time, prevent the great Abuſe of Ticket-buying, and enable Seamen to reap the Benefit of their Labour themſelves, as now they do not;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56570:10"/> and though the King ſhould give 20 <hi>l. per Cent</hi> for Mony ſo to Pay them, his Majeſty would ſave vaſtly by it: And upon iſſuing out his Royal Proclamation at any time, have Men ſufficient for his Service again.</p>
               <p>And here it may be Objected, (perhaps from a Book lately ſet out by one <hi>Henry Maydman</hi> a Purſer) That Seamen are diſcouraged from Their Majeſties Service, by the Abuſes of their Commanders: To which it is Anſwered; It is a ſign that that Purſer hath Sailed with honeſt Captains that would not let him pinch the Men, for the Men never fare better than when a Captain and Purſer diſagree: I obſerve he carefully conceals his Employ of Purſer, well knowing, that of all Officers, ſuch a one in this Caſe is the leaſt to be Credited; for let Commanders ſee that the Purſers do not wrong the Men, and let them be paid their Majeſties Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the Tickets at Payment of the Ship, or upon tender afterwards, they are very well encouraged, and care not for hard words from a Captain, which break no Bones.</p>
               <p>☞ But that which diſcourages Seamen is, the want of their due Pay, and the lying of their Tickets ſeveral Years without Payment, unleſs ſold to a Ticket-buyer, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions the Proverb among them Of going to Sea for a Knife and Sheath.</p>
               <p>This would likewiſe prevent the Impreſſing of Land-men, (altogether unqualified, which often breeds Sickneſs in the Fleet) as alſo Water-men that were never at Sea, upon whom it is now very hard: For Inſtance a Water-man is Impreſt out of his Boat that has a Wife and four or five Children to maintain, in his abſence his Boat is unimployed and receives damage; his Wife and Children muſt become burthenſom to the Pariſh, or if ſhe has Credit, perhaps runs her Husband in debt more than he can get up in a Year or two.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe when a Ship comes home after a long Voyage, the Men are Impreſt, who perhaps have ſome of them Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on Board, which they are ſnatch'd from without hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the liberty of going to their Families, and diſpoſing of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56570:11"/> what they have, or even to refreſh themſelves; in which Caſe their Ventures are loſt, the Men Diſſatisfied, and their Families half Ruined: Alſo, many Perſons have been loſt on the <hi>Thames</hi> and other Places, in endeavouring to Eſcape; as particularly Ten or Twelve Perſons lately in Boats were Drowned, Shot, and Died of their Wounds, in making off from from a Ship that had Preſt them; and the Sand-Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at <hi>Plymouth</hi> when a Preſs is thereabouts, lye wholly Unemployed by the Abſconding of the Men, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Working of Husband-men, for want of that Sand to Manure the Ground; ſo that many Teams of Horſes and Yokes of Oxen, lye ſtill on that account, to the great Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Country.</p>
               <p>This would alſo prevent the great Abuſes by Perſons pretending to be Preſs-Maſters, who to get Money, often do very ill things; ſometimes occaſion Murder, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſuch Diſorders as bring an Odium upon Their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Fleet undeſerved.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it is very hard upon Lieutenants, who in Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing cannot but ſpend more than their Pay, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are Turned out for Impreſſing thoſe that have Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, (which by this will be taken off:) So that no Man, as the Caſe now ſtands, would be a Lieutenant, were it not for the Proſpect of being advanced to Captain.</p>
               <p>In the next Place it is hoped, no Man's Private Intereſt will be thought equivalent to Ballance againſt ſo great a Publick Good and Eaſe as this will be to the King and Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons that have induced me to undertake this great Work, are drawn from my Dear-bought Experience when Priſoner in <hi>France,</hi> where I lay two Years and two Months under great Hardſhips, and Nineteen Months of that time all alone in an uneaſie and Diſconſolate Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>☞ When I was firſt brought Priſoner thither, I lay four Months in an Hoſpital at <hi>Breſt,</hi> for Cure of my Wounds, and was ſent to <hi>Nants</hi> before half Cured. While I was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56570:11"/> at <hi>Breſt,</hi> I was Aſtoniſhed at the Expedition uſed in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Fitting out their Ships, which till then I thought could be done no where ſooner than in <hi>England,</hi> where we have ten times the Shipping, and conſequently ten times more Seamen than they have in <hi>France;</hi> but there I ſaw Twenty Sail of Ships of about 60 Guns a piece, got ready in Twenty days time; they were brought in and the Men Diſcharged, and upon an Order from <hi>Paris,</hi> they were Careen'd, Keel'd up, Rigg'd, Victualled, Man'd and out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the ſaid time, with the greateſt Eaſe imaginable. I likewiſe ſaw a Ship of 100 Guns there, had all her Guns taken out in four or five Hours time, which I never ſaw done in <hi>England</hi> in twenty four Hours, and this with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Eaſe and leſs Hazard than here, which I ſaw under the Hoſpital Window; and this I am ſure I could do as eaſie in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I likewiſe ſaw on the other ſide of the River, an imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Ship with a Tire of Guns, where the Men were often Exerciſed and inſtructed in the Practice and Uſe of the Great Gun, as if they were at Sea, which very much contributed to their Skill; and if the ſame were done and practiſed near our Sea-Ports, it would be of great uſe in fitting Men for the Sea-Service; in which we need not be aſhamed to learn of them, for they are ready enough to imitate us in any thing for their Advantage.</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid Ships being ſo ſoon out again, put me upon Enquiry how the Men were got ſo quickly, and I found that the Seamen were all Regiſtred by the <hi>Intendant Marine,</hi> or Commiſſary of each Province near the Sea, which puts that King to vaſt Charge in paying great Salaries to them, their <hi>Provoſts Marine, Arches</hi> and other Officers for taking Account of all Maritime Affairs, for a Merchant Ship cannot go to Sea without leave from ſuch <hi>Intendant,</hi> who appoints what Seamen they ſhall have, and ſo many Land-men to be trained up in the <hi>French</hi> King's Pay, as is thought neceſſary; which Method he hath uſed for theſe Fourteen Years paſt, in all probability, in hopes of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56570:12"/>
               <p> Theſe Officers Regiſter not only Seamen, but Watermen, Fiſhermen, and all other Perſons belonging to the Sea, or Trading in any River of <hi>France,</hi> as the <hi>Loire, Seyne,</hi> &amp;c. who upon Proclamation are always to be ready to ſerve on Board the Fleet, as they have been all this War, and upon Failure (by his Arbitrary Power) Hangs them up at their own Door without Tryal or Mercy.</p>
               <p>So that to the wonder of the World (tho he has not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Tenth part of Merchant Shipping, as aforeſaid, which is the Nurſery of Seamen) he gets out his Fleet ready to Fight the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> who are ſo much Superior to him in Naval Strength, that it is very much Admired at Abroad, and look'd upon as ill Conduct in us.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>French</hi> King when his Fleet is out at Sea, is at much greater Charge than we, in regard of the Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement he then gives to his Officers, both in Pay and Proviſions, which brings his beſt Nobility to his Service, who when they are ſufficiently Qualified, are Preferred to Command, and never makes Maſters of Merchant-men Captains of Men of War, well knowing that there is as great an improbability in moſt of them, to well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Nature and Command of a Man of War, as 'tis for a Gentleman of 500 <hi>l.</hi> a Year (that perhaps knows well enough how to manage his own Eſtate) underſtands Martial Diſcipline to Command in a Caſtle in a time of Action, or for a Captain in the Militia to be as fit to make a General-Officer, as one that has been in ſeveral Campains, Sieges, and other Actions; and will ſooner prefer one of his Warrant-Officers that has been trained up in his Service, than one of them; tho that is alſo very rare, for he will ſooner Reward them with Money for any brave Action, and give his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to his People of Quality.</p>
               <p>☞ And tho the <hi>French</hi> King by the Means aforeſaid, is at more Charge than we, when his Fleet is out, yet when they come in he is at much leſs, for then he pays off, and lays up his great Ships (as we may now do by the following Method) which ſaves him vaſt Charge in the Winter, when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56570:12"/> his Men go out a Privateering, and make a Harveſt upon our Merchant-Men, which he Encourages by giving them his Tenths of what they take: Which I could wiſh was done in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I cannot forbear mentioning one generous Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that King, who as he Puniſhes well, takes care like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to Reward well: For when I was taken in the <hi>Ports<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> by the <hi>Chevalier Demany,</hi> Knight of <hi>Malta,</hi> in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, a Ship of 60 odd Guns (all Braſs but twelve) tho' he could not bring my Ship in, ſhe was ſo much diſabled, he dying in forty eight Hours of his Wounds, told the Second Captain upon his Death-bed, That nothing troubled him, but that he ſhould die in debt to his Relations and Friends, which being repreſented to <hi>Monſieur Saignelay,</hi> (who then was on Board the Fleet) and by him to the <hi>French</hi> King; the King thereupon did much regret the loſs of ſuch a Man, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He had rather have loſt the Ship than the Captain,</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Payment of his debts, out of his own Bounty, which came to 22000 Livres, which is near 1800 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling.</p>
               <p>Thus it being the Method of the <hi>French</hi> King to furniſh himſelf with Seamen on any occaſion: 1. By Regiſtring them: 2. By his Arbitrary Power, Hanging them in caſe of Deſertion, thereby like Death, ſparing none to the Sea or Gallows. In <hi>England</hi> it would be found both difficult, charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and needleſs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It would be very difficult as well as chargeable to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter Seamen here, becauſe not one in ten is a Houſe-keeper, and therefore not with any certainty to be found.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It would be needleſs, in regard we have not occaſion (as the <hi>French</hi> have) to take all our Seamen, but a moderate Proportion only, which may be done by Regiſtring all ſorts of Shipping and ſmall Craft, uſing the Sea, or any River, Port or Harbour in <hi>England, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> as Merchant-Ships of all ſorts, Fiſhing-Boats, Oyſter-Cocks, Row-Barges, Weſtern-Barges, Lighters of all ſorts, Tricker-Boats, Hiber-Boats, Stow-Boats, and the Trows at <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> Smacks, Hoys, Ketches, Coaſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (by what Names ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Differenced) and giving them a certain Number, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56570:13"/> Mark of Diſtinction, as is done to the Hackney-Coaches, That each of them according to their ſeveral Burthens, Trade and Profit, ſhall find one Man or more for Their Majeſties Service, or be obliged to pay Five Pounds into an Office to be Erected for that purpoſe, for each Man ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered for them to furniſh for one Year, which Office may be called, <hi>The Office for Registring Shipping and ſmall Craft:</hi> And in caſe of failure after a Months Notice given by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to Forfeit to their Majeſties the Ship or Veſſel they ſhall refuſe or neglect to furniſh men for: And that this may not ſeem an Hardſhip upon the Subject, it ſhall be herein demonſtrated, that it is the Intereſt of all Perſons concerned to comply herewith, and that the Money or Forfeiture is not the thing deſired, for if they can provide Qualified Men under that Rate, or for nothing, it is the ſame thing to us, for the Money ſo given, is to be beſtowed Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis on ſuch Men as will go in the Service.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">It is Propoſed,</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Reaſons are,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>I. <hi>That every Oyſter-Cock, Fiſhing-Smack or Hoy for Trawling and Drudging, ſhall find a Man Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and every three Peter-Boats the like, to Serve Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties in time of War.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Becauſe they offered the late King <hi>James</hi> (if they might be Incorporated) that they would find him 500 good Men to Serve him at Sea on any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and now great part of theſe People have Protections, and Serve not at all, tho 'tis more Reaſonable they ſhould Serve the Preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than the Late, and this way their <hi>Quota</hi> will hardly amount to more than they Voluntarily offered before.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>II. <hi>That each Ballaſt Lighter find two Men, tho they have but two Men work on Board them. There are now but Sixty Six Ballast Lighters, tho they ought to be Eighty; but Sixty Six will find a Hundred thirty Two Men.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Theſe Men are Protected by their great Intereſt, and very fit to Serve Their Majeſties. They will in a Tides time take up twenty or thirty Tun of Ballaſt, which comes to about 30 <hi>s.</hi> of which the two Men that Labour hard have but one Third between them, the other two Thirds are divided between the Ballaſt-Office and owner of the Lighter, who having ſo great profit for little or nothing, the Lighter being not worth above 60 <hi>l.</hi> and all Foreigners pay 4 <hi>d. per</hi> Tun more than others, ought to contribute toward the Defence of the Sea, which their profit comes by.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56570:13"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>III. <hi>That each Row-Barge, and Tilt-Boat, find Two Seamen as above.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Theſe Men are fit for the King's Service, and what they uſually givefor Protections may be near ſufficient to find the Men propoſed.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IV. <hi>That each We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Barge, carrying 12 or 14 Men, may find four or five Men, and more or leſs according to the number of Men they Employ.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Theſe Barges have a great and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Profit, pay no Cuſtom or other Duty; and now when they come for <hi>London,</hi> leave their Men at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> at Charge, and hire others there, that are not liable to be Impreſt, ſo that they would willingly contribute to be free and eaſie.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>V. <hi>That each</hi> Ware Barge, and ſuch like find two Men at the leaſt.</cell>
                        <cell>For the Reaſon aforeſaid.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VI. <hi>That all Coal-Lighters, Cloſe-ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſuch like find one Man</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>They now pay for Protections, and by that means have very good Men for 14-5. a Week, and get vaſtly by bringing Coals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> through Bridge, having 12 <hi>d:</hi> for the Carriage of each Chaldron, beſides the advantage of the Meaſure if they be Woodmongers.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VII. <hi>That all ſmall Craft,</hi> viz. <hi>Ketches, Hoys, Smacks, Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Traders, &amp;c. not exceeding forty Tun each, find a Man.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>This they would gladly do, that they might not be liable to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, and get by it too, in regard they might then make the more Voyages, when they have no Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56570:14"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VIII. <hi>That all Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for every Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Tun they Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, at Ninety Five Foot each Tun, ſhall find a Man.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Colliers by this, would be much the gainers, in ſaving the extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Charge they are now at for Men, ſometimes giving <hi>8l.</hi> a Man each voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which at other times they might have for 30 <hi>s.</hi> and when their Men are Preſt in the Swin or Gun Fleet, they are forced to give 40 <hi>s.</hi> or 3 <hi>l.</hi> a Man to be brought up the River. I have known ſome Colliers clear 4 or 500 <hi>l.</hi> in a voyage, all Charges paid: They will make five or ſix Voyages in a year, now this War time, and by this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod may make more.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IX. <hi>That all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Ships, Trading beyond Sea, or lying at home by the Wall, find a Man for each fifty tun they meaſure, and if they are not like to go to Sea that year, and thereof give notice to the Office, (when they bring the Men or pay the Mony, that a Memorandum of it may be Enter'd in a Book for that purpoſe) and if after a 12 Months time they come again, and make Affidavit, that ſuch a Ship has not been at Sea in that time, the Office ſhall repay them two Thirds of the Mony they have given or paid for their Men.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>When they have made a Voyage and come into <hi>Plymouth,</hi> or other places, their Men are Preſt, their Goods it may be periſhable, and their Markets loſt, or to prevent that, they are at vaſt Charge in hiring Men, or procuring Protections to bring their Ships about, ſo that it would be their Intereſt thus to contribute, to ſave them the much greater Expence they are now at as aforeſaid, ſome Ships having to my knowledge given four and five Pounds a Man, for Hands, to bring them up to <hi>London</hi> from the <hi>Downs.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56570:14"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>X. <hi>That all Ships or Veſſels belonging to</hi> Ireland, New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>or other Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and trading hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be obliged upon their coming to any Port of</hi> England <hi>to give ſecurity to find their Quota of ſuch Men during the War.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Becauſe being Subjects to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and liable to be Impreſt as others are, they ought, for their Freedom, to contribute towards the War, in regard alſo that their Safety is concerned in the Publick Good; and alſo many Ships this War for want of Hands (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſſed there out) have been caſt away and taken.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XI. <hi>That no hired Ship or Veſſel Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Service, on any account whatſoever; for carrying Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Stores, Soldiers, or otherwiſe, may be exempted from this Contribution.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Becauſe ſuch Exemption would occaſion many Diſputes, and great trouble to the Office, and be made uſe of as a Pretence, whenas theſe Men receiving their hire (which they will take care ſhall be ſufficient) they ought as well as others to find their Quota.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XII. <hi>As to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termen in the River of</hi> Thames; <hi>it is thought reaſonable, that every three Boats or Wherries ſhould find a Man, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empting the King's, Queen's, or No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemens Watermen, who have Badges and Coats, which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally protect them, and abundance others wear</hi> Bromagem <hi>Coats, as if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to Noblemen and Gentlemen, tho they do not, thereby deceiving the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, and keeping themſelves from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Impreſſed.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Suppoſe there are 6000 Watermen belonging to the <hi>Thames,</hi> one third part of them are at Sea already, Preſt or Voluntiers, ſo that the reſt at home have the benefit now of what main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them all before, and therefore three Wherries may well find one Man more eaſie than a Hackney-Coachman can pay 5 <hi>l.</hi> a year, when he is at ſo great charge in keeping of Horſes, and continual wear of his Coach. None of the Servants belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King, Queen Noblemen or Gentlemen are exempted from paying the Poll, and other Taxes; and ſince they are always paid by their Maſters for what they do, even beyond what others would, and have Coats and Badges given them, tho it be allowed that their Perſons ſhall be protected from going to Sea themſelves, yet they ought to pay their Quota, to find Men as well as their ſhare of other Taxes, and the rather in regard of the Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement they have always had at Sea, where a Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Apprentice that has ſerved him five year is allowed 23 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, when a Captain's or Warrant Officers Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice that hath ſerved five years actually at Sea, has but 18 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, and by this Method the King will have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Good Men inſtead of Boys, uſually ſent by the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termen.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56570:15"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>XIII. <hi>That all foreign Built Ships contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute one 3d part pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to their Burthen, more than Ships Built within their Majeſties Dominions, or what other Proportion the Parliament ſhall think fit.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>This hath been done on other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, for the Encouragement of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navigation, and to put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt home Built, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Bottoms.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>This Method is intended to comprehend all Veſſels and ſmall Craft throughout <hi>England,</hi> as the Sand-barges at <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> to find one Man, and the Keels at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> one Man or more; the Cobles to the Northward, and all manner of Fiſhing-Boats, and ſmall Craft to pay proportionable to the Method before propoſed.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe that Ship-Carpenters, Calkers and Sail-makers, as their employs relate to the Sea, ſhall furniſh ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Men from their ſeveral Yards, for their Majeſties Service, as ſhall be thought Equitable, and Armorours are ſent by the Office of Ordnance.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56570:15"/>
               <p> And to render this Method the more effectual, it is thought neceſſary that the Maſters of all Ships, Veſſels and ſmall Craft that are to find a Man, ſhall bring one qualified Seaman for each Ship, or be obliged to go themſelves, tho they may be excuſed from bringing the reſt of their Quota, on paying 5 <hi>l.</hi> each; and this cannot be reckoned hard, conſidering the great Trouble and Charge they are now at for Protections, which by this will be ſaved, and that is conſiderable; for ſometimes it hath coſt Men more in obtaining Protections than would pay their Quota according to this Method for ſeven Years.</p>
               <p>And to make it the eaſier upon Maſters and Owners of Ships, that they may not be at all the charge for finding their Quota, if it be not provided, that no private Seaman ſhall have above 30 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, which would make them amends; It may be however enacted that all Seamen in Merchant-ſhips ſhall pay to their reſpective Maſters and Owners towards their Charge in finding Seamen for their Majeſties Ships, half a Crown in the Pound for all Mony they ſhall receive for Wages over and above 23 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, that as they are ſo great Gainers by the War, they may be aſſiſting to the War, having now ſometimes 3 <hi>l.</hi> a Month, whereas in time of Peace, they have but 23 <hi>s.</hi> and 25 <hi>s.</hi> a Month; and a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in a Collier has now 8 <hi>l.</hi> a Voyage which uſed to be but 30 <hi>s.</hi> So that by this way the Maſters and Owners will rather gain than loſe, and no one will be prejudiced, for the Seamen pay only out of their extraordinary Wages.</p>
               <p>And in caſe a Veſſel exceed 50 Tun, and amount not to 100 Tun, if ſhe be above the one half of the 50 Tun, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, ſhe ſhall find a Man for that, as well as if ſhe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured the full number; but if ſhe come ſhort of the one half of the 50 Tun, in diſpute, then ſhe ſhall not find any thing, for the odd Tuns ſhe meaſures over and above, even fifties; the Meaſurers to be ſworn to do Juſtice between King and Subject, and to be ſuperviſed by the Commiſſioners of this Office, as occaſion offers; this to be underſtood as relating to Ships going Voyages by Sea, and not In-land Veſſels.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56570:16"/>
               <p> And by this Method inſtead of having 2 or 300 Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants a Preſſing, and forcing Men to go againſt their wills, we ſhall now have 5 or 6000 Men going about with mony in their hands to get Men for their Majeſties Service, who will hereby be encouraged to go willingly, which will be a great eaſe on all ſides, and more expeditious than before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> may be better led than drove, and a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Boy is better than an unwilling Man.</p>
               <p>Perhaps it may be objected, that it will be hard for a Ship or a Veſſel lying by the Wall, to contribute in this manner, and others for Covetouſneſs, or ſome ſiniſter Ends of their own, to get the Charge taken off themſelves, may ſtart other Objections.</p>
               <p>It is anſwered; It is no more hard for a Ship lying by the Wall thus to contribute, than for an empty Houſe to find a <hi>Militia</hi> Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On the the other hand all good Men, and well-wiſhers to the Government (ſo far as I can find, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing them) are willing to it, as knowing that it will ſave them great trouble and charge in Protections, when they may at all times have Men cheap, and free from being Impreſſed, to follow their occaſions, and beſides have Convoys more ready to attend them, when the Fleet is well Mann'd, the Ships clean, and all in good Order: And I am very well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there will not be one Ship or Veſſel the leſs on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but if any Objection be made by thoſe Concerned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Particular hereof, it is humbly deſired they may be perſonally heard themſelves by a Committee, what they have material to offer, as plain matter of fact, (without Lawyers) and we do not doubt but to give good Satisfaction therein.</p>
               <p>This being duly put in Practice all over <hi>England, Wales,</hi> &amp;c. according to the Method propoſed, will it's not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (with Eaſe, when the Office is Settled) furniſh Their Majeſties Fleet in a Month's time on any Occaſion, with at leaſt. Twenty Thouſand Seamen, if not more, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Men than now, becauſe then the rate of Wages, will fall from the preſent Unreaſonableneſs, occaſioned by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56570:16"/> and People will take them that will Serve the Cheapeſt, and ſo be content with the worſe Men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but the King cannot have ill Men, becauſe they muſt be all Qualified as abovementioned, and Examined to that Purpoſe by the Commiſſioners appointed for this Office, who muſt be ſuch as have been Commanders of Men of War, and no other; and ſuch men as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, ſhall have ſome Paper or Atteſtation under their Hands, before they be received on Board any of Their Majeſties Ships of War: And in caſe any Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall bring one Man to the Office, and after Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Approbation, ſhall ſend another in his Room, he or they ſo Offending, ſhall Forfeit to Their Majeſties 20 <hi>l.</hi> for every ſuch Offence, to be Recovered as is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>under mentioned, and paid into this Office for the Uſes aforementioned, in regard the Commiſſioners are anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Their Majeſties for all Unqualified Men ſent on Board Their Majeſties Ships of War.</p>
               <p>And if any Maſter, Owner, or other concerned, refuſe or neglect to find ſuch Man, or Men, to be approved of as aforeſaid, or to pay the Five Pounds for each Man, within the Month Limited by Proclamation, he or they ſhall Forfeit the Ship or Veſſel for which they have not found Men, or paid their Money as aforeſaid, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered into this Office, by Proſecution in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> or at Common-Law, and to be by the Officers thereof Sold and Employed in the Encouraging ſuch Qualified Seamen as ſhall be fit for Their Majeſties Service; for which Encouragement or Gratuity many will be willing to come in; and poor Seamen that come out of <hi>France</hi> and want Cloaths and Neceſſaries, or are otherwiſe Diſtreſſed, will gladly come to this Office and receive Five Pounds to go to Sea, bringing his Landlord, or ſome other Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity to be Bound for his going accordingly, as muſt likewiſe all thoſe that are brought on the account of any Ship, Veſſel, or ſmall Craft; for when any fails, the Veſſel they Serve for, is to be Accountable; and therefore the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56570:17"/> Maſter or Owner on giving his Gratuity, will be careful what Security he has, that his Man or Men ſhall go.</p>
               <p>And that ſuch Maſter or Owner may not be put to any great trouble upon the failure of his Men, when there is any ſuch failure, the Commiſſioners of this Office will ſend to the Maſter or Owner concern'd, for the Bonds of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo failing, and put the ſame in Suit; for which it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived neceſſary, that ſome quick way may be provided for recovering the forfeiture without long Trouble, or unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Charge to the Office.</p>
               <p>And if it ſhall happen that any of theſe Men ſo provided as aforeſaid, ſhall receive Preferment; the Man ſo Preferr'd ſhall be obliged to find another in his room.</p>
               <p>And now for the regular and effectual Management of this great Affair, ſo much conducing to the eaſe and benefit of their Majeſties and their Kingdoms, It is humbly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that there be appointed for the Principal Office in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> five Commiſſioners (all Sea Commanders that have well merited in their Majeſties Service) whereof one to be Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendant, and any three to make a <hi>Quorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there be an Iron Cheſt in the Office, with a Slit on the Top, for any Perſon that brings mony inſtead of Men, to ſee their mony put into, that the King nor himſelf be not wronged.</p>
               <p>That there be five different Locks to this Cheſt, whereof each Commiſſioner to have a Key, and therefore to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened only when they are all preſent, that there may be no Fraud in the Caſe.</p>
               <p>That there be alſo a Secretary, Clerks, Meſſengers, and other Officers neceſſary for this Service.</p>
               <p>That there be a Sub-Commiſſioner for the ſame purpoſe, at the Ports of <hi>Plymouth, Briſtol, Newcaſtle, Yarmouth,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, as thought moſt convenient, with a Comptroller, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, Clerks, Surveyors, and ſuch other Officers as ſhall be neceſſary.</p>
               <p>That there be a like Iron Cheſt in each Port, with three Locks, whereof the Commiſſioner to keep one Key, the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56570:17"/> Comptroller another, and the Mayor of each Town the Third; and the Cheſt to be never opened without the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or being preſent with the Commiſſioner and Comptroller, and ſeeing what mony is taken out, and for what uſe; and that an Account thereof under their and the Mayor's Hand be from time to time tranſmitted to the principal Office in <hi>London,</hi> where an exact Regiſter ſhall be kept.</p>
               <p>That there be a Meaſurer in each Port, and Three for <hi>London,</hi> to meaſure all Ships and Veſſels that they may not be under-rated.</p>
               <p>If it be Objected, that the Creating new Officers neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for this Service, will be another Charge upon the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p>It is humbly Anſwered, That the Officers employ'd are to be ſuch as have well deſerved of the Government; that are diſabled in the Service, and have a Pretence to Pentions or half pay, which by this means will be ſaved, as well as the other great Sums before and after mentioned, to which this Charge is no way Equivalent: Beſides it will be an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Commanders and Officers in the Sea Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that there are Employments capable of Rewarding them, in which alſo they may yet ſerve their Majeſties, and ſo not be a Charge Unprofitable.</p>
               <p>Now for a <hi>Demonſtration</hi> how to raiſe the 20000 Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men propoſed: In the firſt Place, About this time Twelve Months a Fleet of 470 Colliers Loaded at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> came over the <hi>Bar</hi> in two days, and joined 70 Sail more that came from <hi>Sunderland</hi> with Coals, which I am aſſured of by Captain <hi>Banks,</hi> that was then their Convoy; they were from 60 Tuns to 400, ſo that one with another they may be allowed to be near 200 Tun apiece: And at the ſame time thoſe that are Light and Repairing, and Loading at <hi>Newca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> and unloading at other Ports, with what Trade from <hi>Milford,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Wales,</hi> for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>England,</hi> with a ſort of Coal called <hi>Culm</hi> for <hi>Smiths,</hi> cannot be reckoned at leſs than as many more, making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether 1080 Sail, which at 200 Tun apiece one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56570:18"/> may find four Men each, which in the whole raiſes—4320 Seamen.</p>
               <p>There are likewiſe belonging to <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and <hi>Sunderland</hi> about 300 Veſſels call'd Keels conſtantly employ'd in Lading Coals that carry five and ſix Men apiece; and may very well afford to find among them about—500 Men.</p>
               <p>So that the Colliery of <hi>England</hi> modeſtly computed finds alone,—4800 Men, and yet cannot be ſuppoſed to be one ſeventh part of the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then for the Watermen there were this year muſtered on Board their Majeſties Ships of War, 1100 good Men that went voluntarily into their Majeſties Service, who will go again with their reſpective Commanders, beſides thoſe that were ſent by their Hall.</p>
               <p>And we cannot ſuppoſe but that allowing three Boats or Wherries to find a <hi>Man,</hi> without exempting any on account of Privilege: That way there will not go leſs than 1500 or 2000 Men, which muſt be qualified as above, and what Apprentices they ſend that have not been at Sea before, are not to be reckoned in this number.</p>
               <p>The Weſtern Barges, <hi>Ware</hi> Barges, Row-Barges, Tilt-Boats, and Ferry-Boats, will find 500 Men.</p>
               <p>The Ballaſt-Lighters will now find 132 Men, and ought to find 160.</p>
               <p>The Peter-Boats, and Oyſter-Cocks, formerly offer'd 500 Men, and cannot now find leſs, if not more.</p>
               <p>The Coal-Lighters and Cloſe-Lighters are ſo numerous, that I know not what their Quota may amount to. Thus the River of <hi>Thames</hi> furniſhes 3732 Men, without reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Merchant-Ships, and Coal-Lighters, which may be conſiderable.</p>
               <p>In the next place as to the Fiſhery, about Eight Years ſince I was Convoy to the Herring Fiſhery at <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> for two Years, and found that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had then about 700
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56570:18"/> Veſſels employ'd in that Trade, carrying from 8 to 20 Men apiece; ſo that allowing them to carry 15 Men each one with another, it amounts to 10500 Men, and great part of theſe Veſſels belonging to the Cinque Ports, they pretend a Privilege, that they will never ſuffer a Preſs among them, whereby their Majeſties are deprived of the Service of ſo many able men; but by this method their Veſſels will be obliged to find their Proportion, as others do, or pay their mony to provide others; and ſo their Majeſties will have the benefit of their Service, as of Right doth belong to them.</p>
               <p>The Town of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> as I have been informed by the Magiſtrates thereof, hath formerly had 1500 Ships belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it; but now much decay'd by the choaking up of the Mouth of the Harbor.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> had then near 3000 Buſſes and Doggers a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing there, with three ſmall Ships with Flags for Convoy, belonging to <hi>Ankhuſen;</hi> the Commanders coming on Board me all at once, told me, That that Town had once 1500 Buſſes and Doggers belonging to it: Their Veſſels carry above 20 <hi>Men</hi> one with another, being near a 100 Tun each, ſo that at that rate there came 30000 <hi>Men</hi> from that one Town: They make three Voyages in a Year, beginning at the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlands of <hi>Orknay</hi> and <hi>Shotland;</hi> and following the Fiſh through the <hi>Channel</hi> to the <hi>North-Foreland.</hi> Whereas we have the conveniency of taking them up ſo near hand, that at <hi>Yarmouth</hi> what they take in the Night, they can carry aſhore in the Day, and return to their Fiſhing again at Night; whenas the <hi>Dutch</hi> are by their diſtance from home obliged to be at great Charge in Gibbing, Pickling and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling them up to preſerve them Sweet; and muſt lie out at Sea in all Weathers, which we are not expoſed to; and yet to our great Shame and Detriment, both to our Selves and Poſterity, we have in great meaſure loſt that ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Trade of the Herring Fiſhery, which is a Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary for Seamen; and a <hi>Maintenance</hi> to ſo many thouſand Families in <hi>Holland,</hi> who are at much more pains, Charge and Trouble, than we in <hi>England</hi> need be, to whom it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56570:19"/> doth of Juſtice, Ancient Right, and Situation appertain.</p>
               <p>During the time I was Convoy to our Fiſhery there, as aforeſaid; my Buſineſs was to ſee that no Foreigner ſhould Fiſh in ſight of the Shore, becauſe the Fiſh drawing thither to Spawn, the beſt Draughts are there; and beſides the <hi>Waurope</hi> of the <hi>Dutch</hi> is bigger than ours, and their Gear ſtronger; they have bigger Veſſels than we, and more Men, and ſo would be too hard for ours, and drive us off the Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ground, if it were not for our Convoy; for ſome of their Veſſels have 340 Nets apiece, which will reach up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of two mile.</p>
               <p>It happened once I ſaw a <hi>Dutch</hi> Veſſel driving near the Shore, upon which I fir'd a Gun, and brought the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter on Board me; I asked him how he durſt go there to Fiſh, he told me ingeniouſly it was for the advantage of the Draught there; I asked him what Fiſh he had taken that Night, ſeeing his Nets white; he told me 19 Laſt, each of which contains 12000 Herrings, ſo that computing them at 20 <hi>s. per</hi> Barrel, his Nights work came to 228 <hi>l.</hi> with which and what he had taken before, he was forced to run imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to <hi>Holland,</hi> for fear of their ſtinking; ſo that admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting each of theſe 3000 Veſſels take 50 Laſt of Fiſh each Voyage, and three Voyages to be made in one Seaſon, at 10 <hi>l.</hi> each Laſt, it amounts in the whole to 4500000 <hi>l.</hi> This I thought to be incredible; they told me alſo theſe Herrings in paying Duties for Staves, Hoops, Salt, Packing, Import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and again Exporting for the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, bring in a conſiderable Revenue to the State; and then to our great Shame theſe Herrings taken upon our own Coaſt, are likewiſe traded with to <hi>England,</hi> and there ſold for Two-pence apiece, and ſometimes more: And by this it is very demonſtrable what the advantage of this Fiſhery might be, if Encouraged.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> were there, but had not then above 100 Veſſels, tho they (finding the Sweetneſs) have much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed ſince; they would be preſſing in for the Shore; for which reaſon I ſometimes took ſeveral of their Maſters on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56570:19"/> Board me, and then ſet Sail to the open Sea, and there put them all on Board one of their Veſſels to ſhew them Sea-breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and they having no Boats, were two or three days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could get into their own Veſſels again; and this I did purpoſely, that they of all others might not have the Encouragement of over-running us in our Fiſhery.</p>
               <p>The Pilchard Fiſhery in the <hi>Weſt</hi> is very conſiderable, I have known 500 Boats at a time in <hi>Mounts-Bay,</hi> catching Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards: If they be rated according to their ſeveral Burthens, or the number of Men they employ, I doubt not but they will raiſe a conſiderable number of Seamen, as will alſo the <hi>New-found-land</hi> and <hi>Iſeland</hi> Fiſhery, which if encouraged, would turn to good account, and that is no way better to be done, than by letting them have free liberty to Trade, without the Danger of Preſſing their Men.</p>
               <p>And now ſince I have taken the pains to get 20000 Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for their Majeſties Service, which I doubt not but by this Method will eaſily be done, and without oppreſſing any, only laying an Embargo for one Month, and obliging all Maſters and Owners of Ships not to allow above 30 <hi>s. per</hi> Month to any private Seaman; I humbly conceive it but reaſonable ſome Care be taken of thoſe that loſe their Limbs, or are otherwiſe diſabled in ſuch Service, for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the firſt place it is Propoſed:</p>
               <p>1. That the <hi>Poor's Cheſt</hi> at <hi>Chatham</hi> be regulated, and to that end be put under the Care and Inſpection of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of this Office; and in regard that the preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of that <hi>Cheſt</hi> conſiſts of the Seamens Deductions, which in time of Peace fall ſhort, and are of no competent Support for the poor diſabl'd Seamen: It is in the ſecond place Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,</p>
               <p>☞ 2. That if the Law-Bill (which was lately in being) were revived and ſetled upon this <hi>Chest,</hi> for the Relief and Support of Seamen, wounded and diſabled in their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Service; it would not be felt by the Subject, and at the ſame time be a conſtant Fund for this uſe enough to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it; and whereas a Seaman has now at the moſt twenty
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56570:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56570:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56570:21"/> Nobles a Year for the loſs of a Limb, he ſhould then have at leaſt double that Sum, and ſo be Happier without his Limb than with it; for the Smart will be forgot when the Mony is preſent. And here my chief deſign ſhould be to prevent that common Evil too often ſeen in things given to good uſes, that the Pillars to ſupport it, may not be the Caterpillars of it.</p>
               <p>And that this Office may be kept up in time of Peace as well as War, to be ready at all times, for their Majeſties Service; It is humbly Propoſed that all Ships, Veſſels and ſmall Craft, ſhall for each Man they find in time of War, pay 5 <hi>s. per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> in time of Peace, as an Acknowledgment to this Office.</p>
               <p>And that Seamen in Merchant-Ships may not ſtill pretend they have nothing allow'd them, if they loſe their Limbs, whereby many Ships have been loſt, for want of defending them; This Office, in caſe it be thus ſetled, will, for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, pay and allow to all Seamen, wounded and diſabl'd in Merchant-Ships, and likewiſe in private Men of War, two third parts of what is allow'd to Seamen in their Majeſties Ships of War in the like caſe.</p>
               <p>Now to demonſtrate what may undoubtedly be ſaved to the King and Kingdom, by the foregoing Method, I find, that the whole Fleet, by the Liſt of the Line of Battel, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not of 36000 Men, with Fireſhips and Tenders; and now we need not half the Tenders we had before, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no occaſion for them to go a Preſſing.</p>
               <p>And when the great Ships are come in and paid off, that is, the 16 firſt and ſecond Rates, and 18 of the third Rates, with Fireſhips, which together take up about 21000 Men, Officers and all; their whole Pay may be ſaved during the Winter, which at the Method uſual in the Navy, of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 4 <hi>l.</hi> a Man <hi>per</hi> Month, to pay all Wages, Victualling, Wear and Tear, amounts to 84000 <hi>l. per</hi> Month, and that for ſix Months comes to 504000 <hi>l.</hi> At the ſame time we ſhall have a Winter Squadron, which will be 15 third Rates, and 13 fourth Rates, beſides fifth and ſixth Rates. And then we ſhall not want 10500 Men to be at all Calls, by reaſon the others are got already.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:56570:21"/>
               <p> Thus beſides the ſaid 504000 <hi>l.</hi> which may be ſaved each Winter, by paying off the great Ships, there may be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaved 60000 <hi>l.</hi> at leaſt in Conduct, Bounty, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt-Mony, and the hiring Veſſels for Preſſing; ſo that by the whole, it appears, beſides ſaving the King theſe vaſt Sums yearly, his Majeſty will always have Men on any occaſion for his Service, his Ships may be ready to Sail Clean, and in good order: No Pretence can be made uſe of for lying ſtill for want of Men, when the Terrors of Preſſing and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Miſchiefs attending it, are prevented, Protections ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, becauſe no need of them: Merchants and Traders will have their Liberty to Traffick, to their own advantage, as well as the encreaſe of their Majeſties Cuſtoms, and the univerſal good and benefit of all their Majeſties Kingdoms; thoſe concern'd are generally willing to it, wiſhing it had been done before, for that it would have ſaved them a great deal of Mony; and if this be done, I ſhall have the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Serving their Majeſties Effectually upon the <hi>French,</hi> for their Barbarous Uſage to Me; and I doubt not but it will have that Effect, as not only to regain our Ancient Glory, and put us beyond the Danger of being ever attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by them (or any Foreign Enemy) for the Future; but that their Majeſties Royal Navy may go and Command where they pleaſe, and have none dare to oppoſe them.</p>
               <p>And herein I have taken Care as near as may be, not to diſoblige or reflect on any Perſon: But it cannot be avoided, but that ſo great a Publick Good will Retrench the Profit of ſome Officers, as the Secretary of the Admiralty, and his Clerks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who may for that reaſon endeavor to obſtruct and object againſt it; in which Caſe I deſire to be rightly underſtood, that what I do is purely for the Service of their Majeſties and the Kingdom, and not to bring a diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to any Man: But that they may not be Sufferers for a General Benefit, their Majeſties, if they ſo pleaſe, may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate their Loſs by Sallary or otherwiſe, as their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſhall think fit.</p>
               <p>Provided always, that in Caſe any of their Majeſties Men
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56570:22"/> of War, loſe her Men in Action, or by Sickneſs or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and being abroad cannot be ſupply'd from this Office with ſafety to the Ship, ſuch Ship for her Security may Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs as formerly, but ſo as not to diſable any Merchant-man.</p>
               <p>☞ And in caſe this Office be thus ſetled, and that the Law-Bill lately in being, be reviv'd and beſtow'd upon it; It is humbly Propos'd, beſides what additional Encouragement is given to Seamen, wounded and diſabled in their Majeſties Ships of War, Privatiers, and Merchant-men; That there ſhall be likewiſe two large Schools Erected, near a Rivers ſide, in ſome Cheap Country, where the Children of all Seamen kill'd in their Majeſties Service, ſhall be taken into one of theſe Schools, at twelve years of Age, and be there Taught the Mathematicks: That they ſhall lie in <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> Hammocks, which in the day time may be put into Loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that there may be no room loſt for their Lodgings, and every thing be in good order, ſo that then it will be wondred where they Lye,</p>
               <p>☞ That there ſhall be a Ship in the River near the School, where, on Play-days, or other fit Times, the Boys ſhall go on Board, and Learn to Splice and Knot, Reef and Furl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby they may know all the parts of a Ship, and underſtand the Mechanick part of a Sailer, in two or three years time, as well as if they were at Sea; and then they may be drawn off to Sea every year, as occaſion offers, when they will want nothing but to get their Sea-Legs.</p>
               <p>☞ Theſe Youths ſo drawn off yearly, ſhall be put out Apprentice for three Yearsto Commanders or Lieutenants of Men of War, or Warrant Officers in their Majeſties Ships, and not for ſeven Years to Maſters of Merchant-men, as is done to the King's Scholars in <hi>Chriſt-Church Hoſpital,</hi> where, after their Majeſties have been at great Expence in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation for three Years, and in putting them out Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice at 40 <hi>l.</hi> charge in Mony and Clothes; they are Bound for ſeven Years to Maſters of Merchant-Ships, who alone have the benefit of them, without any advantage to their Majeſties or the Youths, tho at their going out they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56570:22"/> as to their Qualification for the Sea, and perhaps are better Artiſts than the Maſters they are put to, whereas if they had never been Taught any thing, or were even took out of the ſtreet, they might as well be put out for half the Mony, and the Maſters be bound to teach them as much as theſe; and after all the Charge their Majeſties are and have been at on this Account, and that there are Ten drawn off to Sea every Year, for theſe 18 Years paſt, there are not now Ten of them in their Majeſties Service, tho otherwiſe there might have been many, had they been Bound to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders or Officers of Men of War.</p>
               <p>☞ There are a great many People have entertain'd a Notion that thoſe bred up in Merchant-men are better Seamen, than thoſe bred up in Men of War; but to undeceive them in this Particular, it is evident, that a Cruiſing Man of War in two Months time plows more Sea, and wanders further between Heaven and Earth, than a Merchant-ſhip does in a Year, by reaſon he Chaſes every Sail he ſees to diſcover what they are; when as a Merchant-ſhip, like a Carrier's-Horſe, goes only the direct Road, to come at his Port the neareſt way he can; beſides he is heavy laden, ſo that a Man of War runs two Foot to his one: Then he is oblig'd to ſtay her for Freight, and often for Convoy, which taken altogether, often keeps him in Port or Harbor nine <hi>Months</hi> in a Year, whereas a Cruiſing Man of War is out at Sea nine Months in a Year; ſo that it is hereby very plain, that in two years there is more to be Learned in a Man of War, both as to Action, the way of Command, and otherwiſe, than by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeven Years in a Merchant-man; but many hold this Argument, hoping thereby to be thought to underſtand the Sea.</p>
               <p>The other School ſhall be for the Sons of Commanders kill'd in their Majeſties Service, and the Sons of Gentlemen, that are willing to be bred up to the Sea, where they ſhall be Taught every thing neceſſary, to qualifie them to make Officers, as particularly Navigation, Fortification, Gunnery, Languages, the Exerciſe of Pike and Musket, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56570:23"/> ſhall be lodged in pretty decent Apartments, and have Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and good Orders among them, ſufficient for their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Inſtruction in things of this nature, which will be of great Conſequence to this Kingdom; and then when it is ſeen that this is well manag'd, it may be preſumed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny well minded People, that have got Eſtates by the Sea, and have no Heirs of their own, may leave their Eſtates or good Legacies to the Support and Maintenance of theſe Schools, which may properly be called the <hi>Academy for the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Encouragement for Commanders and Seamen in Their Majeſties Service, for Taking the Enemies Ships, Goods and Effects.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>I. <hi>THat all Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be taken by any of their Majeſties Men of War, ſhall be forthwith Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Admiralty Court, without any account given to the Prize-Office, and be ſhar'd among the ſhips company, which ſo made her Prize, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to the uſual Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. This was done the laſt</hi> Dutch <hi>War, when the Swan Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier being taken by Captain</hi> Young, <hi>his then Majeſty King</hi> Charles II. <hi>bought her of the ſaid Captain, and made her a Man of War in the year 1675. As alſo the Hunter in like manner bought of Sir</hi> John Berry.</cell>
                        <cell>AS to Privatiers, that great Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement ought to be given for the taking of them, by reaſon they are in a ſtate of War and Defence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their Majeſties Commanders do come to an Engagement with them, and oft find them well Man'd, wherby they not only deſtroy thoſe Ships of Prey, which greatly diſturb the Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and Commerce of the Kingdom, but kill and leſſen the number of their Mariners, and conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the Naval Force of the Enemy, and leaves our Merchant-men the better liberty to Trade.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:56570:23"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>II. <hi>All Ships of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>taken out of the Enemies Harbours, Ports, Creeks, or from and under any Caſtle, Fortification or Fort, or off, or from the Shore, or at Anchor under any Head-land, by any of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Men of War, together with any Goods, Effects and Merchandiſe, that ſhall be ſeized by them, ſhall be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſhared as aforeſaid.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>That all Commanders that ſhall take the Enemies Ships by dint of Sword from under their Guns, ought to have the Encouragement thereof, for that they run an extreme risk, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and danger of their Lives, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giving the Enemy conſtant Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms, making the People uneaſie, and putting them to a great Charge in Guarding their Coaſts, beſides bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an advantage to their Majeſties in their Cuſtoms, of ſuch Goods ſo taken thence; And that if the Prize be taken at Anchor, it may neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs not be diſputed, for that it is to be ſuppoſed all Men during the time of War, will Anchor in as great Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as may be.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>III. <hi>All Merchants Ships and Goods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Enemy and taken as Prize at Sea, on Board all Foreigners,</hi> viz. Swedes, Danes, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſe, <hi>and other Nations, that ſhall be taken trading with their Majeſties Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, with Contraband Goods, ſhall be Condemned in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty, and one third of her lading ſo Condemed, be given to the Captain, Officers and Seamen, that ſo took her as Prize, and paid to the Captain as ſoon as the Commiſſioners receive the Mony, and not according to the former method at ten days after payment of the Man of War, which is not ſometimes till two or three years after.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>That this Encouragement will put the Commanders to a ſtrict ſearching of all Foreign Ships for Contraband Goods, which otherwiſe would ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be view'd, or for a ſmall Sum of Mony prevail'd upon to ſuffer them to purſue their ſeveral Voyages, to the great Diſſervice of the Nation; but the hopes of this will put them upon the contrary Deſign.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56570:24"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IV. <hi>That all Salvage adjudged for Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Ship, ſhall be diſtributed to the Captain and Ships Company, according to ancient Cuſtom, as likewiſe one 3d part of the Goods taken and Condemned from</hi> Swedes <hi>and</hi> Danes, <hi>&amp;c. Wheras now if thoſe Ships be not Condemn'd, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter has no benefit of the Goods that are Condemn'd, thro' the want of a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made full to that purpoſe, which is very hard upon the poor Sailers in their Majesties Service, who by that means have got nothing all the War.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>This Encouragement will hinder any Embezelment, being made after retaking a Ship, and cauſe the Captain to take more care in ſeing her brought ſafe into Port. And by this the poor ſailers will be certain of getting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when their Proportion is aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by Proclamation; whereas at preſent, if one of their Majeſties Ships weakens her ſelf to ſend a <hi>Swede</hi> or <hi>Dane</hi> into Port, he may be in danger by hapning to meet with one of his own rank; and beſides the Seamen put on Board the <hi>Swede</hi> or <hi>Dane,</hi> are in danger of having the Ship retaken, and being carry'd into <hi>France,</hi> where they fuffer great hardſhip, and for all this, as the Caſe now is, have no benefit, if the Ship as well as the Goods be not Condemn'd.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>V. <hi>That all Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that ſhall meet with and Fight the Enemy, to the utmost extremity, and being over-power'd, ſhall happen to be taken, and his Ship ſunk, burnt, or ſo extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſabl'd, that they cannot carry her off, but are either forc'd to ſink or burn her themſelves, the ſaid Commander ſhall be allow'd the full value, of what he makes out to have loſt by the ſaidCapture, and ſhall receive his full pay the time of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity; and in Caſe he the ſaid Captain be diſabled in his Limbs or Body, as not being able any more to go to Sea, ſhall have a Pention during the Interval he ſhall be otherwiſe taken Care of, and provided for.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>That the Encouragement mention'd therein will put all Commanders upon the Emulation of behaving themſelves valiantly, to the utmoſt extremity; encourage the Nobility and Gentry to ſend their younger Children to Sea, when as they find that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment makes a competent Proviſion for them, (as now the contrary has a different Effect) And this Article being the Caſe of a great many honeſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, is the rather hoped will be taken into Conſideration, for that it is of great Conſequence to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Service, and generally obſerv'd in all Governments, that Rewarding well and Puniſhing well, is the chief means of being well ſerved; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis hoped this will be put into Execution for Encouragement at Sea, which is our chiefeſt Strength.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:56570:24"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">How to Share a Prize Taken by a Man of War.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Reaſons for the Sharing a Prize, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Method on the other Side.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>I. <hi>The Moiety of what the King gives in any Prize is to the Captain, and the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be paid into his Hands, to be ſhar'd among the Ships com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, after paying one fifth part to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief of the ſquadron, or Fleet; ☞ Tho Admiral</hi> Ruſſel <hi>has been ſo generous not to take any thing on that account during this War. I ſhould be glad that I could ſay ſo of all the reſt of the Flag-Officers.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Captain having a Moiety, is in regard of his being anſwerable for any Plunder made before the ſaid Prize be brought into Port, and delivered into the Prize-Office, in which caſe he alſo loſes his own Share; and as he has the Care and Conduct of the Ship, and is liable to anſwer for all miſdemeanors, it is thought reaſonable he ſhould be allow'd one half according to ancient Cuſtom, and have the Diſtribution of all ſuch Mony, as the King in his Bounty ſhall think fit to give in ſuch Caſe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>II. <hi>The Lieutenant or Lieutenants, are to have ſeven Shares</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Lieutenants having 7 Shares (which is one ſhare more than the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter has) is in reſpect to hisCommiſſion, and that he Commands the Maſter.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>III. <hi>The Maſter Six Shares.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The maſter having ſix Shares (which is one more than the reſt of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant-Officers) is in regard he Commands them.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56570:25"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IV. <hi>The Miniſter, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, and all War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant-Officers, five Shares.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Maſters-mates, tho not War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant-Officers, have five ſhares as well as they, in regard upon the Watch they Command the Warrant-Officers.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>V. <hi>Maſters-Mates, as Warrant-Officers, five Shares.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VI. <hi>Midſhip-Men 3 Shares.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Midſhip-Men have 3 ſhares, as being Officers, and having a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the Seamen.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VII. <hi>Gunners-mates, Boat-Swains-Mates, Carpenters-Mates, Chirurgions-Mates, and all of that degree to have three Shares.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Warrant-Officers Mates, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving command of their reſpective Crews, are thought fit to have three Shares.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>VIII. <hi>Quarter-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Quarter-Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Cockſons, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals; and all of that Rank to have two ſhares.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The other ſmall Officers have two ſhares to make a diſtinction betwixt them and the Seamen.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IX. <hi>And ſo able Seamen, and ordinary Seamen, to have one ſhare each.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>If this be put into a Proclamation, that all Men may know what their reſpective Shares of Prizes taken will be, it will cauſe a great Eaſineſs in the Fleet, prevent Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and making Parties there, which are more likely on this account than any other, and if any ſuch Diviſions there be, their Majeſties and the Kingdom are the loſers by it.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons of the differences betwixt the Captains of Men of War, and Commiſſioners of the Prizes, are firſt the undue Appraiſements; Secondly, The great Embezelments which they meet with from Prize-Officers, which often puts the Captains upon Plundering the Ships before they deliver them in.</p>
               <p>To prevent theſe Inconveniences, the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals are humbly offer'd, whereby the King may not be Cheated, and the Captain and Ships Company may have Right done them.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:56570:25"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Propoſals.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>The Reaſons.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>I. <hi>When any Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſhall bring or ſend a Prize into Port, and deliver her into the Prize-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, appointed for the Appraiſement of the ſaid Prize, on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the King, the Captain to be there, or ot choſe two others in his Abſence, whoſe Names ſhall be ſent to the Commiſſioners Prizes, who ſhall give them power to Act along with the two</hi> Cuſtom-Houſe <hi>Officers, and Prize-Officers in the Appraiſment of the ſaid Prize.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Two <hi>Custom-Houſe</hi> Officers are conceiv'd neceſſary to be joined with the two Prize-Officers, that the King may not be defrauded of his Cuſtoms as formerly, and the Captain being there, or two in his behalf, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any Fraud to the King, himſelf, or the ſhips Company.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>II. <hi>That for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Goods ſhall be Appraiſed in ſmall Quantities (and not whole Ships Cargoes together, as formerly) which will be a great Augmentation to the price.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>That the Goods Appraiſed in ſmall Quantities, will give liberty to ſmall Merchants to buy, whereby the price will be much augmented, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage both of the King and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>III. <hi>That the ſaid Goods ſo Appraiſed be ſold afterwards by Inch of Candle, and ſet up at the price Appraiſed, by which Means the value will again be much augmented, and prevent any thing of Fraud.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Goods being ſold by Inch of Candle after Appraiſed, will prevent any Fraud or private Contract, which wrongs either King or Subjects, and will much heighten the value of Goods.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IV. <hi>The Sale will be free and publick, and timely notice given to all Perſons, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to the Appraiſers, who ſhall be allow'd to bid, ſo that neither the King nor the Captain be wronged.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>The Sail being free and Publick, the Appraiſers, Cuſtom, and Prize-Officers, are free to bid, being to be ſold to the beſt Chapman.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56570:26"/>
               <p> It is conceived neceſſary, that there be a Seaman Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller of the Prize-Office, which would be a great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to their Majeſties, and make all ſides eaſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Encouragement for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Privatiers.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> private Men of War, as ſhall take any <hi>French</hi> or other Enemies Privatiers, or Ships, having Letters of Mart, may have the whole without Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tenths; by reaſon in doing this, they venture their Lives and Eſtates, for the Publick Good, ſuch Prizes being but of ſmall value.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That all ſuch Prizes as ſhall be taken off the Enemies Shore, or at Anchor under any Fort or Caſtle, or within any Port, Harbor, Road, Headland or Creek of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Country, may pay no Tenths, by reaſon of the great Hazard and Danger the Men thereby run of their Lives and of loſing their Veſſels, which will not be done without En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That they may pay no Tenths for any Salvage, that ſhall be adjudged to them for Retaking any <hi>Engliſh</hi> or Friend's Ship, by reaſon they have often Retaken ſmall Veſſels, for which they have had but a fifth part, amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to not above the Charge of bringing them in, and the Charges of the Law, and yet have been obliged to pay Tenths of ſuch Fifths, to their great Diſcouragement, the which is ſo much the more reaſonable to be condeſcended to, for that ſeveral Ships have been Retaken, which have paid his Majeſty 2 or 3000 <hi>l.</hi> each for Cuſtom,</p>
               <p n="4">4. That whereas many Ships, that have lain in Ports, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors and Roads of this Kingdom without any Seizure or Moleſtation of the Vice-Admirals or Governors, have been found out to be the Enemies Goods, and ſeized by private Men of War, and Condemn'd as Prize, the ſaid. Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals or Governors have very much obſtructed them in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56570:26"/> the Condemnation thereof, and ſometimes after Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation have claimed the ſame to their Uſe, or the Uſe of their Majeſties, to the great diſcouragement of private Men of War, without whoſe Diligence and Intelligence they had never been diſcover'd or ſeiz'd: Therefore it is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that in ſuch Caſes they may have no Moleſtation or Impediment, but have their Prizes according to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, which grant them all they ſhall take, as well in Ports or Harbors, as upon the Sea.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the Tenths of all other Prizes may be remitted to them concern'd in private Men of War, for their Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, for the Reaſons following, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. The <hi>French</hi> King doth at this time do the ſame, which hath ſo Encouraged their Privatiers, that they have fitted out many Ships of good force, and much annoy'd and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd our Trade; the <hi>French</hi> Privatiers having taken about 600 of our Ships, whereas their Men of War have not taken Sixty.</item>
                     <item>II. This Encouragement will enable the Concern'd, to fit out better Ships than now they have, and get Men to Man them by contracting to take Care of all ſuch Men as ſhall be Wounded, and the Wives and Families of them that ſhall be Kill'd or Drown'd, which at preſent they cannot afford to do.</item>
                     <item>III. There is more Reaſon to make this Remiſſion of Tenths to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> private Men of War, than the <hi>French,</hi> in regard of the Prohibition, and the ſmall Trade of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Whereas it may be objected, that unleſs ſome Officers be put on Board each Prize, the private Men of War will be at liberty to do what they pleaſe, and ſuch Officers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be maintain'd without Duties to bear the Charge: It is anſwered, That each private Man of War, at the taking out of his Commiſſion, doth not only oblige his Ship, ſelf and Owners, but alſo gives two other ſufficient Securities in 3000 or 1500 <hi>l.</hi> Bond, not to abuſe their Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56570:27"/> or Allies, but to make Satisfaction for all Injuries done by them, and to pay Cuſtoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſides the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe</hi> Officers preſently put Waiters on Board, to look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Cuſtoms, which the private Men of War pay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without Charge to their Majeſties; And by this propos'd Encouragement, the Cuſtoms will be Encreas'd by the Prize-Ships, ſo that it will pay twenty times more than their Majeſties have or will receive for Tenths: And Beſides, the Encouragement of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Private Men of War, will be very beneficial to this Kingdom, not only in the Encreaſing of Cuſtoms, and weakning the Enemy as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, but in breeding of Seamen, they being oblig'd by their Bonds to carry two thirds Landmen, and but one third of their Complement Seamen.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And if it be objected, that by thus Remitting the Tenths, the Advocate, Receiver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> employ'd therein, will loſe their Salaries; the Propoſer humbly hopes it will not be thought Reaſonable, that the private Intereſt of two or three Perſons, without advantage to the King or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be preferr'd before ſo great a Publick Good, as this Encouragement would be both to the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>Laſtly. It is demonſtrable, that this Encouragement to Privatiers, will prove of no ſmall advantage to his Majeſties Cuſtoms, for Example, they frequently Retake rich Ships, prevent Ships being taken, and one Ship retaken, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brings in more Cuſtoms to his Majeſty than the Tenths will amount to in a whole Year; ſo that both his Majeſty and Subjects will be much the Gainers by this Means: Therefore 'tis to be hoped theſe Propoſals will meet with their Majeſties Compliance, for that their Majeſties may at firſt give it only for a Year, or what time they ſhall think fit to ſee the advantage of it, and afterwards to do therein as they pleaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56570:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
